A Guide to the Heslip M. "Happy" Lee Papers, 1915-2003
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
- Correspondence, October 1967-May 1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Once contained in a spiral bound notebook, nearly 215 items of correspondence (almost half of which are copies of letters sent by Lee), several reports and other items are in this folder. The correspondence and other material are arranged in chronological order by Lee, relates to Lee's work at Shaw University; Urban Affairs Specialist and Consultant, North Carolina State University; chairman of the North Carolina State Advisory Committee to the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights; and consultant to CAP (Community Action Program), the federal anti-poverty program, on his visits to localities throughout the South. Also included is the text of an editorial by WRAL-TV (Raleigh, North Carolina) commentator Jesse Helms (future U.S. Senator), April 16, 1968, concerning Shaw University president Dr. James E. Cheek and the perceived student unrest in Raleigh following the assassination of Dr. Martin Luther King. The editorial on WRAL-TV stationery also comments on an upcoming University sponsored event titled "Congress for the Unity of Black Students" that includes African American activists Leroi Jones and Ron Karenga were among the expected quests. Helms later served in the U.S. Senate from 1972 through 2001. Items of note also include: a letter dated May 23, 1968 addressed to Robert L. McCan of Washington, D.C. by Lee on Lee's upcoming appointment as consultant with North Carolina State University in Raleigh to develop a Community Development Program for Raleigh. This letter also mentions various job offers, Vietnam, and Lee's family; a letter from October of 1968 that explains that over the past four years Lee has served as a consultant to the Office of Economic Opportunity and the Office of Equal Health Opportunities, in Mississippi, Tennessee, South Carolina, Georgia, North Carolina, and Virginia; a letter by U.S. Senator Fred R. Harris (Democrat from Oklahoma) dated June 15, 1968 inviting Lee to participate in a "Crisis in the Nation" conference to be held at the University of Oklahoma; a news release signed by Lee, dated June 25, 1968, from the North Carolina State Advisory Committee to the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights urging every School Board in North Carolina to abolish school segregation; and for researchers interested in the issue of fair housing and the integration of neighborhoods, a "Report on conservations" between the president of the Raleigh Board of Realtors and the Raleigh-Subcommittee, of the North Carolina State Advisory Committee, dated February 26, 1969 (Lee, chairman of the committee, was present at the meeting) may be of interest.
- Correspondence December 1967-November 1968 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Approximately 65 items of correspondence make up this once bound folder. The correspondence was arranged in chronological order by Lee. Much of the material concerns Lee's work at Shaw University. Letters of note include a March 6, 1968 letter from Dr. Ralph Bunche (1904-1971), Nobel Prize winner for peace, then under Secretary of the United Nations, to Lee accepting Lee's request for Bunche to address a joint meeting of students from Shaw University and Saint Augustine's College in May of that year. A letter dated March 22, 1968 from Bunche's secretary informed Lee that Bunche had gotten ill and would not be able to attend the event. A memo dated May 10, 1968 notes that Lee's coordinating 500 people into ten buses from Marks, Mississippi, as the first individuals on their way to the Poor People's March on Washington, D.C. In a May 14th letter, Lee declines an offer to serve as Vice President of Stetson University in Deland, Florida. The folder also contains the text of comments by Lee made February 12, 1968 at his welcoming to participants to a "Consultation on the Urban Crisis and the Negro College" held at Shaw University.
- Correspondence, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Just over 50 items of materials that were once bound arranged in chronological order by Lee make up this folder. The items date from February 16, 1968 through December 18, 1968. It was during this time period that Lee served as Vice President for Development at Shaw University and as Acting Chairman of the North Carolina State Advisory Committee of the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights. Correspondence worth noting includes a letter dated May 20, 1968 from Orville Freeman, Secretary of the U. S. Department of Agriculture, to Lee concerning a recent ruling by the Attorney General of the United States that "allows us to prohibit discrimination in making loans to associations" by the Agricultural Credit Insurance Fund; three letters by a Raleigh citizens group called the "Committee of 17" regarding their concern over desegregation plans in that city and of their concern over the possible relocation of a prison unit from a white suburban area to a black neighborhood (addressed to the Governor of North Carolina, dated August 19, 1968). The folder also contains a listing of the 1968-1969 officers, staff, and board members of the North Carolina Council on Human Relations and a listing of the members of the North Carolina Advisory Committee of the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights.
- Correspondence, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  This folder contains 109 items of correspondence arranged chronologically by Lee all of which were bound. The items date from January through December of 1969. It was during this time that Lee began work as Deputy Director of the Multi-Purpose Training Center of Atlanta University. Much of the correspondence concerns his work in North Carolina, Georgia and as consultant on issues of race, poverty, and urban affairs.
- Correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Over 100 items of correspondence, arranged chronological by Lee, make up this folder of materials that were once bound. The items date from January of 1970 through December of 1971 while Lee worked as Deputy Director of the Multi-Purpose Training Center of Atlanta University and then as Assistant to the Dean, School of Urban Life, Georgia State University. Much of the correspondence concerns his work as consultant on issues of race, poverty, and urban affairs. Included in the folder are reports and memos written by Lee on his work as consultant and the two different universities.
- Correspondence, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  About 60 items of correspondence from February 1972 through December 1972 while Lee served as Assistant to the Dean, School of Urban Life, Georgia State University are included in this folder. All of the items are in chronological order and were once bound. The folder is highlighted by several long memos by Lee to Dr. Alex B. Lacy, Jr., Dean, School of Urban Life, documenting Lee's work. Much of this work concerned projects developed by Lee and funded by the Ford Foundation and Department of Urban Development to finance African American students in obtaining their Master of Science degrees in Urban Administration. Lee would later estimate that approximately 100 students participated in these programs.
- Correspondence, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Just over sixty items of correspondence dating from 1973, all of which was arranged chronologically and was once bound are in this folder. During this time period Lee finished working as Assistant to the Dean, School of Urban Life, Georgia State University and became program officer of the Southern Regional Council based in Atlanta.
- Correspondence, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Sixty-six items of correspondence arranged chronologically and was once bound Lee worked as program officer at the Southern Regional Council. His work brought him back to Virginia to help organize a Center for Public Interest to be based in Richmond, Virginia and correspondents include Lt. Governor Henry Howell of Virginia and Mr. Sydney Lewis of Richmond.
- Correspondence, August 1974-December 1974 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Just over 100 items of correspondence arranged chronologically and was once bound. Lee worked as Southern Regional Council as program officer.
- Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  57 items of correspondence arranged chronologically and once bound. Lee's work in Southern Regional Council. Includes a letter by Lee dated to fellow Board Members of the Southern Regional Council dated June 17, 1976 expressing Lee's strong concerns over the direction of the Southern Regional Council.
- Correspondence, 1977-1983 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  Just over 50 items of correspondence arranged chronologically all of which was once bound. The folder includes Lee's application for a Georgia teaching certificate and his transcript records. Also includes a 1986 essay by Lee on retirement.
- Correspondence, 1980-2003 and n.d. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  Over 70 items of correspondence including items from his family, Democratic Party related correspondence, and letters from school children to Lee on his talk to them about Martin Luther King, Jr. from 1985.
- Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  26 items of correspondence, including correspondence related to his ministry and others.
- Correspondence, 1984-2002, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  Over 60 items of correspondence including items concerning Lee's work in the Democratic Party that includes correspondence from U.S. Senator Max Cleland. Other correspondence is related to his ministry.
- Correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  36 items of correspondence originally bound much of which relates to his ministry.
- Correspondence n.d. (Box 5, Folder 8)
- "Defending the Common School in Democracy," 9 September 1982, Text of speech, delivered at Symposium on Religion and the Humane Society, Wake Forest University, James Dunn, Executive Director, Baptist Joint Committee on Public Affairs. (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Educational Talent Search Program Proposal, 1969-1979, For North Carolina State University, St. Augustine's College. Prepared by Happy Lee. (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Farmer's Club of the Atlanta Chamber of Commerce Annual Banquet, program, 1951-, Honoring the winning communities in the 1951 North Georgia Farm Community Improvement Contest. (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Final Report, Race Relations Seminars, 1972, Sponsored by the National Endowment for the Humanities and the Urban Life Center, Georgia State University. Prepared by Happy Lee, Coordinator, 1 March 1973. (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Final Report to Dr. W.L. Turner, Administrative Dean for University Extension, North Carolina State University, 15 June-31 August 1968, From Happy Lee, Urban Affairs, Specialist and Consultant, North Carolina State University. (Box 6, Folder 5)
- "For a Better Understanding of Aging and the Aging Process," 28-30 June 1971, This event was sponsored by the School of Urban Life, Georgia State University and the Senior Citizen Services of Metropolitan Atlanta, Ind. (Box 6, Folder 6)
- The Gauntlet, October 1958 and February 1959, Newsletter of the Baptist Student Union, Mercer University, v. 6 no.2, February 1959; and one page of the October 1958 issue. (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Good Friday Mediation, St. Christopher's Episcopal Church, Springfield, Virginia, by Heslip M. Lee, 15 April 1960 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Grant Application for Title III Funding, Saint Augustine's College, November 1972, Written and compiled by Happy Lee. (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Handbook of Community Organizations, City of Atlanta, Urban Life Center, Georgia State University, June 1974 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Happy Lee Family Jewelers, sales slip, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Happy Lee Jewelers, catalog, 1982-1983 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- "Human Relations Night" ticket, International League Baseball game, Richmond, Virginia, 9 August 1963, Parker Field desegregation event organized by Happy Lee. Also contains two invitations to Happy Lee to dinner and cocktail party by the Union Leader Corporation related to Baseball Dinner in Manchester, New Hampshire. (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Inscription by Bobby D. Doctor to "Laura and Happy," n.d., Doctor was interim chairman for the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights. (Box 6, Folder 14)
- John Deere Day itinerary, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Checking account books, 1977-1981, 1982-1988 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Lee Family Genealogy n.d., Descendants of Bennett B. Lee (1813-1894) and Mary Ann Sheets Lee (1835-). (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Legal Pad Notebooks n.d. (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Listing of foundations who give to Black Colleges and/or causes espoused by Episcopalians n.d. (Box 7, Folder 3)
- "Marvelous Man, A" 1999 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Materials related to Congressman Bob Barr of Georgia n.d., 1998-2000 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Metro Atlanta Chapter of the National Association of Human Rights Workers, address list, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Miscellaneous items collected by Happy Lee, ca. 1960-2003, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Miscellaneous items written by or collected by Happy Lee, ca. 1960-ca. 1980, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous mailing lists, 1972, 1973, ca. 1980-1990 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Miscellaneous notes, printed material, and other materials, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Miscellaneous poems and other written salutes to Happy Lee by colleagues and others, 1985, 1986, 2002, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 11)
- "Motives Stranger than Fear", text of radio address by Ralph W. Sockman, 27 February 1944, "National Radio Pulpit" season of 1943-1944, National Broadcasting Company, no. 22, WEAF and Network. (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Newspaper Clippings [see box 16] (Box 7, Folder 13)
- North Carolina Association of Collegiate Registrars and Admissions Officers official program and flyer, November 1969, Happy Lee was a speaker at this event. (Box 7, Folder 14)
- North Carolina State University newsletter, 1968, Article on Happy Lee and his employment as Urban Affairs Specialist and Consultant. (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Notes, 1963-1964, Concerns demonstrations, integration, Civil Rights legislation, and other issues written by Lee. (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Photographs of Lee family, ca. 1920 (Box 7, Folder 17)
- Photograph of Coretta Scott King, Governor of Utah, and Happy Lee, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Photograph of Lee, Coretta Scott King, and Bill Clinton at a campaign rally, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 19)
- Photograph of Happy Lee Family Jewelers building storefront, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 20)
- Photograph of Happy Lee, ca. 1960, Two different images. (Box 7, Folder 21)
- Photograph of Happy Lee, ca. 1989-1990, Two images. (Box 7, Folder 22)
- Photograph of Happy Lee receiving an award at Georgia State University, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 23)
- Photograph of Happy Lee and the Lee family, ca. 1950, Two images. (Box 7, Folder 24)
- Photograph of Happy Lee and Laura Lee, ca. 1990 (Box 7, Folder 25)
- Photograph of Happy Lee from War on Poverty, 1967-1968, Two images. (Box 7, Folder 26)
- Photograph of Happy Lee with Jimmy Carter, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 27)
- Photograph of Happy Lee with Senator Max Cleland, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 28)
- Photograph-Heslip "Happy" Lee with film director Anthony Thomas, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 29)
- Photograph of Madison Avenue Baptist Church, 2003, Photos taken by Ed Peeples. (Box 7, Folder 30)
- Photograph of Walter Mondale and Geraldine Ferraro, 1984, Campaign photo taken in 1984. (Box 7, Folder 31)
- Photograph of NAACP convention in New York City, July 1959 (Box 7, Folder 32)
- Policemen's Institute, two programs, September 1979 and December 1980 (Box 7, Folder 33)
- Political activity materials, 1990-2001 and n.d., Consists of miscellaneous publications, correspondence, and other Democratic Party items. (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Polk County (Georgia) Democratic Association materials, 1990-2000 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Polk County (Georgia) Democratic Association's Jefferson-Jackson Dinner speech, 25 May 2001, Text of speech by Laurie S. Lee about Happy Lee. (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Polk County (Georgia) tax receipt, 1929, Paid by Jim H. Lee. (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Postcard of Colgate-Rochester Divinity School and Chapel, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Postcard of Republican House Restaurant, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Program "Happy and Laura Lee's 50th Wedding Anniversary," 7 July 1991 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Proposal for an Upward Bound Program, 1969, Program sponsored jointly by Saint Augustine's College and North Carolina State University. Prepared by Happy Lee. (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Proposal to the Mary Duke Biddle Foundation for Faculty Improvement, 20 January 1971, Submitted by Saint Augustine's College and prepared by Happy Lee. (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Proposal to the Max C. Fleichman Foundation for Construction of a Library Building, 21 February 1971, Submitted by Saint Augustine's College and prepared by Happy Lee. (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Publications, 1967-2003 (Box 8, Folders 11-20)
  - 40 Documents of the Freedom Train, Priceless Historic Documents of Our Heritage and Freedom, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Church and State, July-August 1999 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Georgia Trend, April 2003 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Intelligence Report, Spring 1997 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Katallagete Be Reconcile: Journal of the Committee of Southern Clergyman, Fall-Winter 1972 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - The Other Side, Christians and Homosexuality, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - The Present Dilemma of the Negro, 2 November 1967, Address given by Kenneth B. Clark before the Annual Meeting of the Southern Regional Council. (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Ramparts, May 1968, Includes the article "In White America: The Execution of Dr. King." (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Scarce, Rare, Out of Print and Used Books on Black America, Race, and Racism,, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Who's Who in Training and Development, 1971, Official membership directory of the American Society for Training and Development. (Box 8, Folder 20)
- Readings for Race Relations Seminars, 27 September-15 November 1972 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Report of the North Carolina State Advisory Committee to the United States Commission on Civil Rights concerning Fayetteville and Cumberland County, North Carolina, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Reports of the Executive Director to the Board of Directors of the Salisbury - Rowan Community Service Council, Inc., 10 March and 20 May 1966 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Right-Wing Propaganda in Print from a Commentary on Regional Extremism of the Right, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Saint Augustine's College-Policemen's Seminar, Ethics in Civil Law program, 28 January-1 February 1974 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Salisbury-Rowan Community Service Council, Inc., Application for Manpower Development, 21 April 1966, With an introduction written by Happy Lee. (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Shaw Plan, 1967-1968, Official catalog of Shaw University. (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Shaw University Bulletin, October 1968, Article on Happy Lee concerning his employment. (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Shaw University, Upward Bound Proposal, 2 January 1968, Written by Happy Lee. (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Shiloh Baptist Church (Brunswick, Georgia), souvenir program, 8 February 1970 (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Southern Baptist Theological Seminary newsletter, 1954 (Box 9, Folder 11)
- State of Georgia, Board of Education certificate for Happy Lee, 1949 (Box 9, Folder 12)
- State of Georgia, Decade for Action to Combat Racism on Racial Discrimination proclamation, 28 September 1973 (Box 9, Folder 13)
- Speeches and Articles on the Urban Crisis, 1967-1968, Collected by Happy Lee. (Box 9, Folder 14)
- Seventh District Democratic Party stationary, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 15)
- "Tension and Conciliation: a Report on Contributing Factors Causing Racial Disagreements and Conflicts with the Hickory, North Carolina, City Schools," 1974 (Box 9, Folder 16)
- Various articles collected and bound by Lee, ca. 1968 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Virginia Council on Human Relations, "The Church and the Virginia Council on Human Relations," December 1964, Term paper written by seminary student James Hayden Howell. (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Virginia Council on Human Relations, concluding report by executive director Happy Lee, 4 December 1964 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Virginia Council on Human Relations, miscellaneous materials, 1961-1963, Principally consists of newspaper clippings and partial reports. (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Virginia Council on Human Relations, miscellaneous publications, 1964 and n.d. (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Virginia Council on Human Relations, newsletter, November 1961 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Virginia Council on Human Relations, program for farewell dinner for Happy Lee, 3 December 1964 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Virginia Council on Human Relations, annual conference program, 28 April-1 May 1970, Conference held in Roanoke, Virginia. (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Virginia Council on Human Relations, report on the activities of Happy Lee, November-December 1963 (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Virginia Council on Human Relations, reports, September-December 1961 (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Virginia Council on Human Relations, speech for annual meeting by Happy Lee, 23-24 November 1962 (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Virginia Council on Human Relations, survey, n.d., For owner or manager of a facility serving the public regarding segregated serving policies. (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Visitor passes, United States House of Representatives and United States Senate, 1955, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 13)
- Voting Rights Act of 1965, paper by Laurie Suzanne Lee, May 1974 (Box 10, Folder 14)
- Writings by Lee, 1956-1986 and n.d. (Box 10, Folders 15-30)
  - Active Options, September 1986, Article by Happy Lee from International Council of Christian Churches Magazine. (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Assuming a Universal Option, n.d., Commencement address by Happy Lee at St. Paul's College in Lawrenceville, Virginia. (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Busing as a Tool for Desegregation, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - The Denominational College, November 1956, Student paper by Happy Lee. (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - A Greek Tragedy, American Style, Fall-Winter 1972, Vignette by Happy Lee on his life, race, and religion published in Katallagete Be Reconciled: Journal of the Committee of Southern Churchman. (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Hidden Persuaders in Human Relations, April 1962, Text of a sermon by Happy Lee given at First Unitarian Church. (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Human Relations: Problems, Progress, and Prognosis, Fall 1963, Text of a speech at the Bridgewater College by Happy Lee. (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Individual Responsibility and the American Revolution for Rights, 15 November 1963, Text of speech given by Happy Lee before Omega Psi Phi at Virginia Union University. (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Problems with the Confession, n.d., Text of a sermon given by Happy Lee at University Presbyterian Church (Buffalo, New York). (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Profile of a Senior, n.d., Text of essay by Happy Lee. (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Roots of Prejudice, November 1961, Convocation address by Happy Lee at Virginia Union University. (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Sermon on the Resurrection, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - St. Paul's College Baccalaureate sermon, 1962 (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Utah State Senate prayer, 12 February 1986 (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - War on Poverty in the United States, 28 February and 1 March 1966, Speech given at Mercer University (Macon, Georgia) by Happy Lee. (Box 10, Folder 29)
- "Personalities of the South" plaque, 1975-1976, Presented by the Editorial Board of American Biographical Institute. (Box 11, Folder 1)
- "In Appreciation to Happy Lee for Outstanding Service as Principal Organizer in 1995 and Service as President in 1995-1996 and 1998" plaque, 1999, Given by the Polk County Democratic Association. (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Certificate, 12 February 1963, Appoints Happy Lee to the Virginia State Advisory Committee to the Commission on Civil Rights. (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Silver Plate, 1963 1963, Inscribed "Heslip M. Lee For Outstanding Achievement in Human Relations, Omega Psi Phi." (Box 11, Folder 4)